A Guide to the Papers of the Jones Family of Louisa County, Va., 1853-1908
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Other Jones family papers 1853-1860; 1865-1907
  - Mary Helen Jones Sumner to her brother the Reverend John William Jones 1854-1856; n.d. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Eighteen letters describing her activities and events in Louisa Court House as well as events in Charlottesville such as small pox and a temperance meeting with Dr. Broaddus and Dr. McGuffey.
  - Mary Helen Jones Sumner to her mother Ann Pendleton Jones n.d. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Three letters describing her visits with friends.
  - John R. Jones to Gilley Jones 1853 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - The Reverend John William Jones to his sister Page (Willie Page Tucker) 1883-1907 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - John William Jones (Uncle) to his niece Mary Helen Jones Sumner 1858 May 11 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Lute Jones to her borther the Reverend John William Jones 1858 October 6 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - R. Meade Jones to his brother n.d. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Pendleton Jones to his brother the Reverend John William Jones n.d. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Includes three letters from Pendleton while studying at Mr. Thompson's school to John at the University of Virginia. John is helping him to get an appointment as a state student from the district. He wrote to him about studying at the University of Virginia and obtaining a situation as a teacher after one year.
  - Pendleton (temporarily) expelled from school 1858 June (Box-folder 1:22)
    According to a letter from Helen Jones (n.d.) to her brother the Reverend John William Jones, Pendleton was expelled from a school prior to attending the University and the family was mortified. He appears to have had a disagreement with his sponsor/teacher [John Thompson] which may have caused his dismissal. Helen wrote to her brother John about her concern for Pendleton and urges him to write him. There is also a letter from Pendleton to John thanking him for his good advice but refusing to apologize. He wrote that he felt very badly about it and wished he could just go away somewhere. He continued to live at home and Helen's letter reveals that Pendleton was trying to make a living by coming up with a new business idea but his father forbade it as he did not consider it to be a sound business venture. She wrote, "He and [Albin] have taken up a foolish idea that they could make a good deal, by buying a patent right for a washing tub & without consulting anybody, wrote to the men about it, had not entered into any contract before Pa found it out & forbid Pennie from going any farther with it."
    Excerpts from Helen's letter to her brother John are: "We are all very much distressed about Pen at this time. He has not been getting on well at school & Tuesday he and John [Thompson] had some difficulty & he was expelled from school. I never saw Ma & Pa more mortified about anything in my life... Pa does not know what in the world to do with him. I have tried my best to get Pennie to make some apology to John & ask him to take him back to school, but he will not agree to it- I wish John you would write him an affectionate letter & give him some advice- may be you might influence him, Pen's always had more obstinacy than any of the children but I would not have believed he would ever had allowed as to act so impudently." John must have written Pendleton because on June 5, 1858, Pendleton wrote to John thanking him for his advice but still refuses to apologize to Mr. Thompson.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: (letter from Ann Pendleton Jones's sister Georgie) n.d. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Miscellaneous items: shoeshine cloth and photograph of Lieutenant Joe Berret-former mayor of Washington. n.d. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - L.R. Page to (Judy) n.d. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Shomeaker to Edloe Jones 1863 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Crawford Howell Toy to the Reverend John William Jones 1860 (Box-folder 1:27)
    Includes three letters from Crawford Toy to John where he offers advice and discusses his religious activities and their friendship.
  - Anson Tucker to his aunt 1902 (Box-folder 1:28)
    Relatives (descendants) of Jones family
  - Anson W. Tucker obituary 1908 (Box-folder 1:29)
    Relative of Jones family
  - Atlanta Journal and the Atlanta Constitution newspaper clipping on J.G. Berret and the appraisement of slaves 1862 April 20